H. C. Tinsley Collection Relating to John J. Pershing
H. C. Tinsley Collection Relating to John J. Pershing
1919-1920
Tinsley, Howard C.
0.25 linear ft.
Memorabilia, printed material, and writings by and about American General John J. Pershing.
4943804
Biographical History
According to information provided by the donor of this material, Howard Carnes Tinsley (1876-1928) was an American soldier during World War I. He is listed as a staff member assigned to HQ COD [Combat Operations Division?], LoC [Lines of Communication] and later served as American Vice Consul to Uruguay. At some point during his military career he evidently served in some administrative capacity with General John J. Pershing.
John Joseph Pershing (1860-1948) was an American career military officer best know for his service in Europe during World War I. A graduate of West Point, Pershing had a long military career, serving in the Spanish-American War, the Philippines Insurrection, and the Mexican Expedition. During World War I, Pershing was appointed Commander-in-Chief of American Expeditionary Forces in France. When the war ended, he served as Chief of Staff to the United States Army. In 1919, he was awarded the title "General of the Armies of the United States" by Congress, the highest possible rank at the time, making him the only officer in U.S. history to hold the title other than George Washington. He retired in 1924. His memoirs, My Experiences in the World War, were awarded the 1932 Pulitzer Prize for history. During World War II he was a strong advocate of aid to Britain.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The H. C. Tinsley Collection Relating to John J. Pershing consists of memorabilia, printed material, and writings relating to General John J. Pershing, U.S. Army.
Memorabilia consists of a typed document concerning World War I battlefields in France, various invitations and programs for events honoring General Pershing upon his return the U.S., and a list of staff salaries and assignments, including H.C. Tinsley. There is also a color photocopy of three photographs.
Printed material contains several issues of "The Transport Ace," a newsletter printed by and for those aboard the USS Leviathan, and a small commemorative booklet printed for American soldiers heading home.
Writings are all by Pershing (or, possibly, by a speechwriter for him). There is a copy of Pershing's final formal report as Commander in Chief of the American Expeditionary Forces, and several speeches given by Pershing to ladies' clubs, high schools, and other civilian groups in late 1919 and early 1920.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by type or title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948.; Tinsley, Howard Carnes.; Leviathan (Steamship); United States. -- Army -- Officers.; Battlefields -- France -- 1910-1920.; Generals -- United States.; World War, 1914-1918 -- France.; United States -- History -- 1919-1933.; United States -- History, Military.; Correspondence.; Invitations.; Photographs.; Programs (documents); Reports.; Speeches (documents); Soldiers -- 1910-1920.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert C. Sewell, whose grandfather was Tinsley's nephew.
Inventory
- Memorabilia
  - Guide to the Battlefields, circa 1919 (Box 1)
  - Invitations, programs. etc., 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - List of staff salaries and assignments, 1920; also includes one typed sheet with some notes on overall organization (Box 1)
  - Photographs (reproductions), 1919; color photocopies of three photographs, two showing Tinsley and one possibly showing Pershing (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - "To the Homeward Bound Americans" by B. Van Vorst, circa 1919; expresses gratitude of the people of France to American soldiers (Box 1)
  - "The Transport Ace," USS Leviathan, Sep 1919 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Reports
    - Final report of Gen. John J. Pershing, Commander, American Expeditionary Forces (Government Printing Office), 1919 (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - Lincoln, Nebraska, Dec 1919; 3 items (Box 1)
    - Mesa and Phoenix, Arizona, 30 Jan 1920; 7 items (Box 1)
    - Fort Worth, Texas, 7 Feb 1920; 1 item (Box 1)